so this is
from ingutura nikaya book of twos
verse 12 and this refrain
is found in many suitors
the buddha says because i have
personally known
two things non-contentment in regard to
wholesome qualities
and tireless striving
and then the refrain that comes in he
says i strove tirelessly
with this attitude in mind willingly let
only my skin sinews and bones remain
and let the flesh and blood dry up in my
body but i will not relax my energy so long
but i will not relax my energy so long
as i have not attained what can be
attained by manly strength
energy and exertion and it was
by that type of heedfulness that i
achieved liberation
that i achieved unsurpassed security
from bondage
it comes down to the obvious in order to
do the right effort you need to know
what the right effort is
because uh usually that that very
um passage
is interpreted in a way that it just
means this
unwavering blind determination
like i just determined that i will not
move from here until i become
enlightened so classy like i watched my breath i
so classy like i watched my breath i
i've heard about alapanasana
so now i'm going to focus my breath
until until my knees pop out of
exactly so that's misguided on on
various levels first level being so
do you know what enlightenment is do you
know exactly
oh i'm right here now my mind is
um free from this much and not free from
these things and so on
this this is the work i need to do to be
enlightened as we would say like a person who
as we would say like a person who
understands he knows what needs to be
done he can see the extent of his mind that
he can see the extent of his mind that
needs to be developed
so do you see that for yourself before
you make a determination
oh okay so this is what i need to
do and train to reach the complete
enlightenment but then you realize no you don't know
but then you realize no you don't know
that yet here you are determining that
you will not move breathe or whatever
else until you become enlightened so you
until you become enlightened so you
don't know what enlightenment is yet
you're making determination
towards enlightenment so then you that's
what i mean it's misguided because in a
sense your
determination is real i mean there were
people who
fully committed to this
but the point is you commit out of this
faith that enlightenment will happen to you
that enlightenment will happen to you
if you exhibit unwavering determination
regardless of whether you know the goal
or not
you just want it hard enough i want it
so much
that i will sacrifice my life in hope
that it will happen to me
they will be given to me and that's not
enlightenment already
so that's when when you read this
passage when the buddha describes
the let my sinews dry out my blood run
up and my
up like just bones and sinews left and
so on
it's to the point of oh you know exactly
what needs to be done
and you will not be and you will not be
careless in regard to that so it's what we said
in regard to that so it's what we said
in other talks like for example you
recognize that
a thought of sensuality is not your
problem accepting the thought of sensuality
accepting the thought of sensuality
welcoming delighting in it
not seeing through it not seeing the
nature of it that is your problem
that's where the problem's there so now
you kind of
already are distinguishing where the
work is other work
is on the level of not entertaining
sensuality not being careless about it not doing
not being careless about it not doing
things that will bring centrality to
increase and non-centrality to decrease
and now i will determine that i will not
waver in that regard
so regardless of what scenario i'm in
what circumstances are there whenever
there is a central thought
i will not give into it so
once you clarify what the work is what
needs to be done
what the training is you make
determination that to that extent of the
training you will not compromise it
that doesn't and then you know okay so
that doesn't mean i need to
sit and not breathe until i reach
enlightenment and die and i said no it
just means
i know what the work is and i will never
compromise on that knowledge
and that's exactly what whatever is to
be obtained by the manly effort
also you what what can you do with a
manly effort well you can do
that which you know how to do you can't
have manly effort but you don't know
what you're supposed to do with it
so with manly effort manly restraint
with determination with the unwavering
um
commitment i will not bother with
sensuality i don't need to get rid of everything
i don't need to get rid of everything
and die in some little
call not eating and not drinking water
until i become enlightened no
but i will not tolerate sensuality
regardless of what circumstances throw
at me
for the rest of my life i will not
tolerate ill will
with a manly effort manly restrained
manly commitment
for the rest of my life oh if it's
normal we'll find
i don't need to train that because it's
not your will i don't need to train that
because it's not centrality
so that entire thing that he determined
was based upon fully discerned path of
what needs to be done
so unless you know what needs to be done
your determination will
be misguided so you should then instead
of determining that like a wishful way
oh may my bones dry up and i will never
move unless i become enlightened
whatever enlightenment might be instead
of doing that which can be very
intoxicating because that determination
just making a blind determination is
yeah it brings lots of energy behind it so
it brings lots of energy behind it so
you can feel very good
but the point is yeah but is it rooted
in knowledge is it rooting exactly what
you need to do or is it really wishful
thinking and as the buddha said himself
the path cannot be obtained by wishing
alone oh may i become enlightened
but yeah are you doing the things that
lead to enlightenment no i don't know
well then you won't become enlightened
someone said i might not know what uh
enlightenment is
or exactly how to get there there you go
so then instead of your
determination being on that level when
you don't even know what it is
why don't you scale it down a bit and
actually apply to things you can know okay so i
apply to things you can know okay so i
don't know what
enlightenment is how about i determine i
will not rest
until i find out what enlightenment is
there you go that's your work already
find out
not to entertain wishful thinking about
enlightenment will happen to me
on account of these random practices
that i took on faith
and mere faith alone
so then you say how do how do you know
what enlightenment is well start reading
the buddhist words
start thinking about it start reflecting
it start questioning what you understood
and removing basically layer by layer by
layer determine that until you know that you
determine that until you know that you
know you will not
rest until you get the right view you
will not rest doesn't mean you'll never
sleep doesn't mean means you will never forget
doesn't mean means you will never forget
that that is your goal
you will never sit down and say
no i won't think about the dhamma now
not because i have something else to do
simply because i don't want to
you won't do that because you determined
to not do that
so when you can you will do it
you will reflect you will you will learn
and then you get to know what an item
is and then you'll know what you need to
do and then you apply the same type of
determination to exactly the right extent the middle
to exactly the right extent the middle
way
not too much to the point of as the
buddha himself tried before
i'll stop breathing and i'll die no that
was an ignoble
way as ignorant essentiality
it's conceited full force nothing really
gets uprooted there
so you want to discern the extent
of the training what the actual training
is oh this is the training okay but do i
see that for myself or have i just
repeated what i heard from somebody else
even if that thing is right thing that
you heard from somebody else
okay so you're doing it but are you
seeing now how
that is the training to what extent your
mind is trained
yeah where is your responsibility with
it the clearer you become about that
the clearer will the easier will be to
determine the right effort towards it the only
the right effort towards it the only
reason people can't determine the effort
towards enlightenment
is because they don't have a clue what
it is they don't even know when where to
start and you as you know yourself whenever
and you as you know yourself whenever
you want to try like learning new things
beginning is always the hardest because
you can't even master that strength to
begin because
you just imagine oh this you don't know
anything about it
but instead of projecting like want to
learn a new language instead of
projecting like your determination on the level of
like your determination on the level of
being fluent
how about i maybe just make a
determination to spend five minutes
of reading the other language a day not
more than that just five minutes
but do it consistently
doesn't matter what comes out of it i'll
just do this
and then before you know it you're much
more familiar the more familiar you
become the new options the new ways of
the new options the new ways of
furthering their training will present
themselves now because you actually started
now because you actually started
building it up from the right level from
the bottom up
not like i don't know anything in
between me and enlightenment
i'll just determine the enlightenment
and then wish it will happen to me
missing all the other steps in between
so that's why as the buddha said it
cannot be obtained by the wishing alone
it just doesn't work like that
and the first thing he said i i knew
non-contentment with wholesome quality well that's the
with wholesome quality well that's the
thing
but not knowing really what the training
is
not knowing what the wholesome is you
will be
discontent in the face of wholesome
you haven't learned the content of the
whole song because you don't see it for
what it is
and then consequently you will be
content with the unwholesome
with the actually harmful for you you'll
be content he was non-content with the
whole system he was not in contact with
the wholesome qualities because
the contentment out of the wholesome
will not come automatically
you need to develop it on account of
sticking to the wholesome
and that's why it's so hard and that's
why as i said so many times before
you cannot arrive at the dhamma
accidentally because see
you got the wholesome thing but it
doesn't feel right
you're discontent about it but if you
discern that it's the right thing
as the buddha himself did and he stuck
to it
the contentment arose from it and then
he was effortless
then the tireless energy arises because
it's the energy you are not making
is the energy that's discerning the
things like like we spoke before the effortless
like like we spoke before the effortless
mindfulness if mindfulness is done
correctly it is effortless
it doesn't require your determination
and you're holding on and then doing it
it's effortless because it's in the
things themselves in the nature of
awareness the nature of being alive it's already
the nature of being alive it's already
has a degree of mindfulness in it
so it's discerning that and tapping into
that on account of right restraint right
on account of right restraint right
effort rounding it up
building it up then it's effortless
that's why you can't have too much of it
or too little of it it's just effortless
because it's just part of the experience
as a whole
so yeah when i suppose
most people read that you know let my my
bones my blood dry up and so on it means
like ascetic practice yeah it means this
intense and you can take it that way
and it could it might be wholesome but
wholesomeness or usefulness of it
will not be determined by your
determination or by the extent of
determination it will be determined by the whether you
it will be determined by the whether you
know what enlightenment is what the
training is or you don't know
so that's why for some people the buddha
said by all means you have to do these
aesthetic practices
but for some people you you shouldn't
but that's not measured by you deciding
that's not measured by you deciding
whether you should or shouldn't it's
measured by you knowing what
enlightenment is and then seeing what
supports it and what doesn't support it
what supports maintenance of that middle
way and what kind of overshoots it or
and what kind of overshoots it or
undershoots
so the measure is the knowledge the
measure of your determination
is the knowledge of the path the right
view what enlightenment is then you'll know
what enlightenment is then you'll know
to what extent that's why
he did not preach when when those monks
david asked him to to make these ascetic
asked him to to make these ascetic
practices which are very like noble and
lofty to make them mandatory for every monk
to make them mandatory for every monk
and it will say no
because actually they would be
detrimental for someone
some mind once they know the
enlightenment if they go too far into a
setting they will obscure
the right level of training of an item
they will not
approve the oculusa some might
if they know the enlightenment they need
the aesthetic level to reach that right
threshold that's why you cannot be made as a
that's why you cannot be made as a
blanket rule you all must do
this you all must do that because
literally not two minds are the same not
two minds are on the same level
i think in society now it airs on the
side of
uh indulgence you know you come way too
comfortable aesthetic practices it does and no well
aesthetic practices it does and no well
i said the predators is always even back
in the time
back in the builder's day we're always
more inspiring
that's good to say if you can do the
aesthetic practices without compromising
the level of of of training for
enlightenment you are practicing for the future
you are practicing for the future
generations then future generations are
going to be inspired on a kind of
enlightenment because they don't have a
clue what that is
but they will be inspired on account of
your aesthetic practice and you always
see that whenever somebody
says it's always more inspirational
that's just factual
but it doesn't necessarily mean that the
individual level it's more wholesome
now sensuality must be abandoned one way
or the other
so when we say that sometimes asceticism
is not wholesome doesn't mean
oh so yeah i could just stay in
sensuality no no no no
that's completely the other level that
must be abandoned through it through
like celibacy is not an option celibacy
is not optional so when we talk about
asceticism we're not talking about the
eight presets
we're talking about taking the eight
precepts on a whole new level
of like eating just a unhoused rice
one handful of it wearing rag robes
sleeping under
uh never sleeping under a roof root of a
tree um never taking medicine never laying
um never taking medicine never laying
down never laying down
those are the ascetic practices so yes
that's a good point because
in some lesson they might confuse
thinking oh i mustn't go into asceticism
too much that's
i don't have to be celibate no that's
absolutely eight precepts is the minimum
for training towards the enlightenment
five precept is the minimum for
basically distinguishing yourself
from an animal behavior as you would
have said
like a wholesome uh worldly behavior
that does not lead to enlightenment just
leads to wholesome behavior and also
come and hold some results of a camera
but if you want to practice for the
worst enlightenment and train for it
eight precepts
is them is the minimum but now eight
presets for somebody
who want to really be fully enlightened
as that that the line says
might not be enough so it doesn't mean
you introduce
16 presets and 50 54 just means the
principles of the 8 precepts now you
need to amplify even more
so like not not sleep laying down
yeah again not out of because you read
that such and such
great rajan did that and you're inspired
to like show how manly
you are and i know it's because you
actually see that laying down
always makes you up wake up with lost
carelessness anger
and then takes you four hours to undo it
so what if i don't lay down
ah there you go you got a practical
basis for your ascetic practice
but based on knowledge what needs to be
developed so if you don't have the knowledge for
so if you don't have the knowledge for
yourself
clearly distinguish free from doubt what
needs to be developed
any of these detail the determination
practices will be utterly misguided and
all going to amplify your conceit as
they did to every single ascetic giant
back in the day that the buddha
mocked and said they were completely
wrong and misguided
so instead your determination should be
pointed to that which you
know that you can develop such as i can
become familiar with all the suitors
my determination can can basically make
me married
all the suitors daily and and make the
effort and when i finish i start again
and again and again until i get the
clarity of the message
now you do need determination for that
to do it every day
to read it and read it and read it
to familiarize yourself with poly you
need determination for that
to keep the precepts you need the
termination for that so all these things
you can actually have
a vast amount of effort applied
full on determination and not as
misguided because you can actually
develop this you're not waiting for the
lightning to happen
on a kind of i'll just never do this
never do this never do that
for no practical base you don't see the
reason why you shouldn't do that
i'll never lay down yet but why is
laying down
on wholesome like having a sexual
intercourse lying or killing
well no so where is your determination
based upon
based in so that's what i mean there's
no practice without the right view
we said it millions of times millions of
times before so you're determining the end
before so you're determining the end
game of the practice without even
knowing what the practice
is it's just contradiction terms